Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  - JAMESON, MRS. ANNA BROWNELL (MURPHY), 1794-1860
    - ALS: Vienna, to Mr. Denis Brownell Murphy, 1835 May 7 (Box 11, Folder 410)
      4 p.; 20 x 24 cm.
      Recounts her relations with the
      Princess Hohenzollern and the
      Countess Zichy.
    - ALS: Traunkirchen, to Mrs. D. B. Murphy, 1835 Aug 17 (Box 11, Folder 411)
      Watercolor sketch on letterhead.
    - ALS: Rosawitz, Bohemia, to Mrs. D. B. Murphy, [1845] Aug (Box 11, Folder 412)
      3 p.; 20 x 25 cm.
      Letters dated: Aug. 17, 27 & 28.
    - ALS: Dresden, to Charlotte Alicia Murphy, 1850 Sep 25 (Box 11, Folder 413)
      4 p. & 2 p.; 14 x 22 cm. & 14 x 11 cm.
    - ALS: Vienna, to her mother, Mrs. D. B. Murphy, and her sisters Eliza and Charlotte, [1850] Oct 16 (Box 11, Folder 414)
      2 p.; 23 x 20 cm.
    - ALS: Vienna, to her mother, Mrs. D. B. Murphy, and her sisters, 1850 Oct 31 (Box 11, Folder 415)
      4 p.; 23 x 29 cm.
    - ALS: Vienna, to Miss Eliza Murphy, 1850 Nov 25 (Box 11, Folder 416)
      4 p.; 15 x 22 cm.
    - ALS: Vienna, to Miss Charlotte Murphy, 1850 Dec 19 (Box 11, Folder 417)
    - ALS: Vienna, to Mrs. D. B. Murphy, 1851 Jan 1 (Box 11, Folder 418)
    - ALS: Vienna, to Miss Charlotte Murphy, 1851 Jan 25 (Box 11, Folder 419)
    - ALS: Dresden, to Miss Charlotte Murphy, 1851 Feb 4 (Box 11, Folder 420)
    - ALS: Weimar, to Miss Charlotte Murphy, 1851 Feb 17 (Box 11, Folder 421)
  - JEAN PAUL, 1763-1825
    Full name: Johann Paul Friedrich Richter
    - ALS: Bayreuth, to Ludwig Tieck, 1805 Oct 5 (Box 11, Folder 422)
      3 p.; 13 x 18 cm.
      Signed: Jean Paul Fr. Richter.
  - JERUSALEM, FRIEDERIKE WILHELMINE, 1759-1836
    - ALS: Wulfinghausen, to "Ew. Wohlgeboren", 1828 Aug 10 (Box 11, Folder 423)
      Concerning receipts for interest
      paid.
  - JOHNSON, W. S.
    - The Devil and Doctor Faustus, by William Leman Rede (Box 11, Folder 424)
      AMs, 5 l.; 27 cm.
      Report of research on the above work,
      undertaken on behalf of the firm of
      B.F. Stevens & Brown, American
      library & literary agents, London
      who were commissioned by Mr.
      William A. Speck.
      With: ALS from the firm to Mr. Speck,
      Feb. 2, 1917 and ALS from W.S.
      Johnson to Mr. Thompson, Jan. 30,
      1917, concerning this research.
  - JOSEF KAINZ' PROMPT BOOK OF ROMEO AND JULIET
    - Prompt book of Romeo and Juliet, used by Josef Kainz, the Austrian Shakespeare actor, for production in Germany (Box 11, Folder 425)
      AMs, 46 l., interleaved with pages of
      printed text; 22 x 12 cm. (Text:
      15 x 10 cm.).
      Interleaved text, without title page,
      is A. W. Schlegel's German
      translation of Shakespeare's Romeo
      and Juliet. Leipzig: P. Reclam,
      n.d., 5-93 p.
  - JUNG-STILLING, JOHANN HEINRICH, 1740-1817
    - ALS: Heidelberg, to "den lieben Bruder Tops", 1805 Jan 13 (Box 11, Folder 426)
      2 p.; 19 x 11 cm.
  - KARL AUGUST, GRAND DUKE OF SACHSEN-WEIMAR-EISENACH
    Dates: 1757-1828
    - ALS: Weimar, to Johann Heinrich Merck?, 1783 Aug 18 (Box 11, Folder 427)
      Signed: C.A.SWE.
    - AD: Ausgaben Karl Augusts aus S. Privatscatoulle, 1825-26 Apr 1 (Box 11, Folder 428)
      1 p.; 30 x 20 cm.
      In an unidentified hand, not Karl
      August's.
      Includes notation of payments to Frau
      v. Heygendorf, née Jagemann, and to
      Jagemann.
    - Document, signed: Weimar, to Franz Ludwig Güssefeld, 1780 May 2 (Box 11, Folder 429)
      Official black seal attached.
      Text within black border.
      Signed: Carl August SWE.
      Decrees that Güssefeld be bestowed
      the "Praedicat eines Secretarii."
    - Document, signed: Weimar, to the Militär General Kommando Weimar, 1824 Mar 9 (Box 11, Folder 430)
      Transfer of an officer from Apolda
      to Kapellendorf; also signed:
      CWFhFritsch.
  - KAUFFMANN, JULIE VON
    Autograph album containing 11 entries by
    teachers and friends of Julie von
    Kauffmann. 1866
    - AMs, signed, 80 unnumb. l. (69 blank); 21 cm. Black embossed leather binding. On cover: Poesie. "Julie von Kauffmann 1866" written on lining paper. The 6th entry, a holograph quotation "Aus den Briefen von Goethe's Mutter," with note "Zum freundlichen Andenken an unsre literarischen Unterhaltungen, Stuttg. d. 3 Sept. 1866," is written and signed by Ed. Mörike. May 24 to Sept. 20, 1866.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 814
  - KEAN, CHARLES JOHN, 1811?-1868
    - Original manuscript stage instructions and cast for Goethe's Faust and Marguerite (Box 12, Folder 431)
      15 p.; various sizes.
      A magical drama, as first performed
      at the Princess's Theatre under the
      management of Charles Kean on April
      19, 1854 and possibly in 1858.
      With the prompter's manuscript
      regulating the entry of the various
      characters, (13 p.).
    - Der Freischutz [!], performed under the management of Charles Kean, [ca. 1854] (Box 12, Folder 432)
      AMs, 32 p.; various sizes.
      Original Ms of the cast.
      Lists several casts, probably for
      different performances, dated Oct.
      3, 1844 and Nov. 4, 1846.
  - KERNER, JUSTINUS ANDREAS CHRISTIAN, 1786-1862
    - ALS, to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 433)
      2 p.; 25 cm.
      With 2 verses in continuation of a
      humorous poem by the recipient
      directed against Fürst Pückler-
      Muskau.
  - KESTNER, CHARLOTTE, 1788-1877
    - ALS: Basel, to Marie Hansen Taylor?, 1873 Nov 10 (Box 12, Folder 434)
      3 p.; 10.5 x 13 cm.
      A picture of Charlotte Kestner will
      be sent on request to Mrs. Taylor
      by the nephew, Dr. Kestner.
    - Autograph note, signed: Basel, to Marie Hansen Taylor, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 435)
      1 p.; 14 x 10 cm.
      Thanking for a letter and giving
      her Basel address.
  - KESTNER, CHARLOTTE (BUFF), 1753-1828
    - Receipt, signed, Hannover, 1822 Nov 21 (Box 12, Folder 436)
      1 p. cut from longer document
      6 x 20 cm.
      Note in lower left hand corner:
      "Original-Unterschrift meiner
      Mutter. Hannover 10. Juli 1865.
      G. Kestner."
      Receipt for rent.
  - KESTNER, JOHANN CHRISTIAN, 1741-1800
    - Autograph receipt: Hannover, for Commissar Meyer at Ramelsloh, 1778 Dec 21 (Box 12, Folder 437)
      1 p. 13 x 19 cm.
      Handwritten note: Handschrift meines
      Vaters Joh. Christian Kestner.
      Hannover Aug. 1865. G. Kestner.
  - KILIANI, LILIAN BAYARD (TAYLOR), B. 1858
    - 11 ALS, to William Alfred Speck, 1920-25 (Box 12, Folder 438)
      28 p.; various sizes.
      1920 Feb 23, Kew Gardens, L.I. with
      1920 Mar 3, Kew Gardens, L.I. with
      1920 May 3, Kew Gardens, L.I. with
      1920 May 11, Kew Gardens, L.I.
      1920 May 17, Kew Gardens, L.I.
      1920 Jun 10, correspondence card.
      1921 Apr 19, Partenkirchen.
      1921 Aug 10, Partenkirchen.
      1922 Dec 10, Partenkirchen.
      1925 Sep 13, Partenkirchen, within
      black border.
      n.d., Kew Gardens, L.I.
      All bearing on her father's interest
      in Goethe.
  - DIE KINDESMÖRDERIN VON STRASSBURG (PUPPET-PLAY)
    - Original prompt-book of "Kindesmörderin" puppet-play, transcribed by Max Kirmse (Box 12, Folder 439)
      AMs, 108 p.; 22 x 17 cm.
      "Der Text ist eine Bearbeitung von
      H. L. Wagners Kindermörderin für das
      Puppen-Theater und dürfte aus den
      1880er Jahren stammen." - Ehrhardt.
      With: Transcript of play.
  - KIRMS, FRANZ, 1750-1826
    - ALS: Weimar, to Secretaire Esperstaedt, 1814 Dec 21 (Box 12, Folder 440)
      1 p.; 21 x 34 cm.
      Request for the transfer of a number
      of the more recent manuscripts of
      Kotzebue's plays from Berlin to
      Weimar, especially that of "Der
      Rehbock."
      Kirms was a member of the Weimar
      Theatre Ways and Means Committee.
  - KIRMSE, MAX
    - AL: Chemnitz, to Georg Ehrhardt, 1913 May 20
      - 1 p., with envelope; 17 cm. Announcing shipment of his transcription of Ritscher's Faust puppet-play text
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, box 4, folder 158.
    - ALS: Chemnitz, to Georg Ehrhardt, 1913 May 30
      - 3 p.; 22 cm. Announcing shipment of his transcription of Albin Richter's Faust puppet-play text; discussing other such texts to be procured. With: Stub of postal shipment card; letter from Frau Thekla Bille.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, box 4, folder 159.
  - KLINGER, FRIEDRICH MAXIMILIAN VON, 1752-1831
    - AL: Giessen?, to Phillipp Christoph Kayser?, [1775] Nov 24 (Box 12, Folder 441)
  - KLOPSTOCK, FRIEDRICH GOTTLIEB, 1724-1803
    - Autograph note: Hamburg, to H. Cammersekretär Schmidt in Halberstadt, 1774 May 6 (Box 12, Folder 442)
      1 p.; 19 cm., mounted on inside of
      folded double sheet opposite an
      engraved portrait of Klopstock.
      Only the last 5 lines are in
      Klopstock's handwriting.
      Announcing shipment of 20 copies of
      "Gelehrten Republik" and giving
      instructions to forward the
      subscription payments to his sister.
      A copperplate was enclosed as a memento.
  - KNEBEL, KARL LUDWIG VON, 1744-1834
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Euer Hochwohlgebohren", 1792 Mar 12 (Box 12, Folder 443)
      Remarks accompanying the return of
      the fifth volume of the
      "Reisebeschreibungen."
    - ALS: Jena, to Löbel?, 1817 Jun 15 (Box 12, Folder 444)
      4 p.; 18.5 x 23 cm.
    - ALS: Jena, to Luise Seidler, 1812 Apr 7 (Box 12, Folder 445)
      2 p.; 11 x 17.5 cm.
    - ALS: Ilmenau, to Prof. Walch, 1804 Jan 24 (Box 12, Folder 446)
  - KOCH, RUDOLF
    - ALS: Stuttgart, to Carl Freiherr Cotta von Cottendorf, 1887 Nov 18 (Box 12, Folder 447)
      On stationery of the J. G. Cotta'sche
      Buchhandlung.
      Congratulations on the occasion of
      Cotta's 25th wedding anniversary,
      accompanied by Almanach von
      Radierungen von M. von Schwind,
      Zurich, 1844.
      Removed from the volume described
      above.
  - KOLFF, JACOB VAN SANTEN, 1848-1896
    Der Faust-Ouverture Werden und Wachsen.
    n.d.
    - Collection of printed and manuscript material, partly mounted on stubs, bound to 24 cm. Discussion of Richard Wagner's Faust- Ouverture. Letters and postcards are in French. Contents: ALS, Kolff to Alfred Bovet, 3 p.; ALS: Berlin 1886, Kolff to Alfred Bovet, with postscript by Mme. C. Kolff, 8 p., with envelope; Der Faust Ouverture Werden und Wachsen, Geschichtliches, Biographisches, Aesthetisches (from Bayreuther Blätter, 17, Jahrg. 1894), p. 240-248,368-375; Ms, Der Faust Ouverture Werden und Wachsen, pt. 2, sect. v-viii, 21 fold. l.; ACS: Berlin 1895, Kolff to Bovet; Grosse Todtenmesse (Requiem) von Hector Berlioz, Programm-Buch, 39, 1 p.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 815
  - KORTÜM, ?
    - ALS: Pempelfort bei Düsseldorf, to Johann Friedrich von Cotta, 1810 Nov 30 (Box 12, Folder 448)
      3 p. on 2 l.; 21 cm.
      The initials before the signature are
      illegible.
      Note at end: Adr. Staatsrath Jacobi.
      Submitting poems by B. H. Freudenfeld
      for publication in the Morgenblatt
      für gebildete Stände.
      No enclosure.
  - KOTZEBUE, AUGUST FRIEDRICH FERDINAND VON, 1761-1819
    - ALS: Reval, to Paul Gotthelf Kummer, 1812 Jan 23 (Box 12, Folder 449)
      1 p.; 19 x 22.5 cm.
      Kotzebue makes suggestions to his
      publisher for the marketing of an
      "Opern Almanach."
  - KRÄUTER, FRIEDRICH THEODOR DAVID, 1790-1856
    - ALS: Weimar, to Allgemeine Anzeiger, Gotha, 1837 Oct 27 (Box 12, Folder 450)
      Enclosure: Autograph note, signed,
      advertisement for a cook, 1 p.
      16 x 21 cm.
      Requesting the newspaper to insert
      the enclosed advertisement.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Carl Strohmeyer, 1826 Sep 25 (Box 12, Folder 451)
      2 p.; 19.5 x 24 cm.
      Kräuter was librarian at Weimar and
      Goethe's private secretary.
  - KRAUKLING, KARL CONSTANTIN, 1792-1873
    - ALS: Dresden, to Johann Peter Eckermann, [1828?] (Box 12, Folder 452)
  - KRAUS, GEORG MELCHIOR, 1733-1806
    - ALS: Weimar, to Friedrich Justin Bertuch?, 1787 Jul 12 (Box 12, Folder 453)
      2 p.; 14 x 19.5 cm.
      Kraus is sending for the Pandora
      Calendar a list of illustrative
      materials, among them "1200
      Köpfgens."
  - KRELING, AUGUST VON, 1819-1876
    - ALS: Nürnberg, to Friedrich Bruckmann, 1876 Feb 22 (Box 12, Folder 454)
      3 p.; 13 x 21 cm.
      A report on the progress of the
      illustrations for Faust von
      Goethe, 1. Theil. Mit
      Illustrationen von A. v. Kreling.
      Munich, Friedrich Bruckmann,
      1874-1877.
  - KRÜGER, KARL WILHELM, 1791-1841
    - ALS: Berlin-Charlottenburg, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1827 Jul 1 (Box 12, Folder 455)
  - KURZ, HEINRICH, 1805-1873
    - ALS: Munich, to Johann Friedrich von Cotta, 1831 Feb 24 (Box 12, Folder 456)
      1 p.; 26 cm.
      Requesting an advance on his
      royalties; hopes to take over the
      translation and editing work for
      Polish newspapers, and asking for
      the letters of Prof. von Raumer
      from France, during the year 1830,
      so he may prepare them for
      publication.
  - LANDON, LETITIA ELIZABETH, 1802-1838
    Afterwards: Mrs. George McLean
    - AMs, signed, translation of four poems with covering letter to W. Jorden Esq., 1834 Dec 26 (Box 12, Folder 457)
      4 p. with address; 23 cm.
      Contents: The Beloved always near.
      Goethe. [Nähe des Geliebten]; The
      Lovely little Flower. Goethe. [Das
      Blümlein Wunderschön]; The Black
      Hunt of Litzow. Körner. [Lützow's
      wilde Jagd]; The Gathering. Körner.
      [Männer und Buben].
      Printed in The Literary gazette; and
      Journal of belles lettres, arts,
      sciences, &c. for the year 1835,
      London, p. 11-12.
  - LANDOR, WALTER SAVAGE, 1775-1864
    - ALS: Bath, to Elizabeth Barrett Browning, 1846 Jul 5 (Box 12, Folder 458)
      3 p.; 11 x 18 cm., with envelope.
      Both letter and envelope with black
      border.
      Landor excuses his delay in replying
      for the reason: "I could not, by
      any exertion of ingenuity, decipher
      your signature. Do you write your
      name in such a manner, that nobody
      may attempt forgery? ... I remember
      to have red[!], fifty years ago,
      Theseus, a Monodrama by Stolberg.
      Of course I mean in the translation.
      It is the only Greek modern thing I
      ever saw. Goethe is so little
      hellenic that he represents
      Iphegenia (a girl of 12 or 13)
      arguing on the injustice done to
      the sex in various ways. His
      tragedy is insufferably dull."
  - LASKER, BRUNO, 1880-1965
    - The Poet as Botanist, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 459)
      4 l.; 28 cm.
      On Goethe.
  - LAVATER, JOHANN CASPAR, 1741-1801
    - ALS: Zurich, to S.A. Fabrizius, 1789 Aug 19 (Box 12, Folder 460)
      1 p.; 18.5 x 23 cm.
    - ALS: Zurich, to Christoph Girtanner, 1785 Mar 8 (Box 12, Folder 461)
    - ALS (fragment): Zurich, to J.G. Herder, 1774 Nov 16 (Box 12, Folder 462)
      2 p.; 19 cm.
      The letter is autobiographical and
      about his work.
      Engraved portrait of Lavater, by
      Heinrich Pfenninger, mounted on
      p.[3] of the double sheet.
    - Sammlung von Gedanken zu einem allgemeinen Organon; oder, einmahl eins des Menschen. 1782 Nov 15
      - AMs on 73 cards; 10 x 7 cm. In slip case.
      - See: Bound Volumes, folder 816
    - 3 autograph poems, 1789-99 (Box 12, Folder 463)
      Um gute Federn auf die Reis [Title:
      An Anna], May 1, 1789, 4 p.; 12
      x 6 cm.
      Freüe Dich Deines Manns, Basel, May
      18, 1799, 1 p.; 5 x 9 cm.
      Komm! Herr Jesu! [Title: Seüfzer],
      Oct. 7, 1799, 1 p.; 9 x 5 cm.
      Removed from Johann Caspar Lavater's
    - Das menschliche Herz. Sechs [i.e. Drei] Gesaenge. 1789
      - AMs, 2 p. l., 153 p.; 17 cm. Not in Lavater's hand. Without music. Manuscript note on t.p.: "Meiner verehrenswürdigsten Fürstinn von Anhalt-Zerbst. 16. Nov. 1789." With dedication to "Ihre Majestät, Charlotte, Königinn von Gross- Brittannien." Underlinings in green ink, and verse numbering in red. All six "Gesänge" pub. as v.1 of his Hand-Bibliothek für Freünde. [Zurich] 1790.
      - See: Bound Volumes, folder 817
    - Lord Chatam, oder Pitts Büste Commentiert, für Heinrich Lips. n.d.
      - AMs, signed, 38 p. diagrs., 4 mounted ports.; 37 cm., with brown board covers. Date on t.p.: Kloten, Sonntags, den 18. October 1789; on p. [30]: Zürich, Dienstags den 13. Jenner. 1789. Signed on t.p. and p.[30]. Four portraits, original pen drawings, mounted and within green and black borders, laid in at end. This essay has never been printed. - Mr. von Faber's old catalogue card.
      - See: Bound Volumes, folder 818
    - Vermischte physiognomische Regeln. Manuscript für Freünde, mit einigen characterischen Linien. Erstes Hundert. Zum Bessten der Armen. 1789
      - AMs, 103 loose leaves; 21 x 13 cm., in box; 23 x 16 cm. Leaf 51 misnumbered 57. Calligraphic writing within black and pink borders; many leaves have line drawings of facial features, illustrative of the text. Vignette with bust of Lavater, by J. Merz, mount. on inside front cover of box. Published in Hand-Bibliothek für Freünde [Zurich] 1793, v.1.
      - See: Bound Volumes, folder 819
    - Stufen, 1-3. n.d.
      - 70 drawings in 3 boxes; 23 x 16 cm. The boxes have labels on inside front cover, numbered 1-3. Original pen and ink drawings of faces, showing features in progressive stages from the crude to the refined; with inscriptions in Lavater's hand. These sketches were not used in Lavater's Physiognomische Fragmente. Box 1, with title "Vermischtes" on spine, contains 25 drawings numbered 1-18; 2, 4-9. The faces, mostly on yellow background within black circle, surrounded by a square ornamental frame; ms. inscription below circle; the whole mounted on strong paper. Box 2, with title "Stufen" on spine, contains 27 drawings numbered 1-8; 18-25; 1-10, 25. The first 2 groups as in box 1, in the 3d group the drawings are within black circle, the inscriptions on labels with engraved border; both mounted on boards covered on recto with blue paper; drawing 15 of the 3d group (Goethe's portrait?), in the same state, is in color and has no inscription. Box 3, with title "Stufen" on spine, contains 18 items: 6 unnumb.; no. 1-4, 1-6. The 6 unnumb. drawings within gold, black and pale green border mounted on boards; nos. 1-4 within black circles surrounded by blue, mounted on light green boards nos.1-6, each containing a drawing of a man in full figure in an attitude of supplication against a round pale green background, which is surrounded by blue, all within black frame and mounted on boards; also 1 mounted engraved plate (18 x 12 cm.) and 1 colored drawing of a peasant woman (14 x 10 cm.); all items bear inscriptions.
      - See: Bound Volumes, folders 820a-c
    - Stufen Box I, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 464)
      AMs, 3 p.; 20 x 13 cm.
      Autograph ms. in an unidentifed hand.
      Analytical description of twenty-five
      drawings of physiognomies by J. C.
      Lavater, intended for publication
      in a facsimile portfolio, which
      was never issued.
      With: ALS: Cleveland, Cornelia
      Blakemore Warner to Christine N.
      Strout at the Yale University
      Library, March 29, 1915, with
      envelope and a typed prospectus of
      the projected publication.
    - Autograph note, 1785 Feb 15 (Box 12, Folder 465)
      2 p.; 6 x 9 cm., mounted.
      A note to a printer on the proof of a
      bordered card; after certain
      improvements he would like at least
      a thousand cards.
  - LAWRENCE, JAMES HENRY, 1773-1840
    - ALS: Paris, to Lady Sydney (Owenson) Morgan, 1819 Feb 21 (Box 12, Folder 466)
      3 p.; 10 x 12 cm.
      Letter of introduction for Mr. Clarke
      Abel, the author of "Narrative of a
      journey in the interior of China,
      1816-17," 1818.
    - ALS: London, to Lady Sydney (Owenson) Morgan, 1820 Nov 3 (Box 12, Folder 467)
      4 p.; 18.5 x 22.5 cm.
  - LEIP, HANS, 1893-1983
    - Goethes Gartenhaus, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 468)
      Poem, published in his Kadenzen,
      Stuttgart, Cotta, 1946, p. 80.
  - LEVETZOW, ULRIKE FREIFRÄULEIN VON, 1804-1899
    - ALS: Trzblitz, to Theodor von Levetzow, 1893 Feb 28 (Box 12, Folder 469)
      5 p.; 15 x 19 cm., with envelope.
  - LEYEN, FRIEDRICH VON DER, 1873-1966
    - Goethe und die Weltliteratur (Box 12, Folder 470)
      31, i.e. 29, l.; 29 x 23 cm.
      6 and 7, and 26 and 27, each on 1 l.
      Typescript (original), with author's
      corrections in pencil.
      Published in Jahrbuch der Goethe-
      Gesellschaft, v.5, 1918, p.
      135-157.
  - LODER, JUSTUS CHRISTIAN VON, 1753-1832
    - ALS: Jena, to "Magnifico Academiae Pro-Rector!", 1786 Oct 28 (Box 12, Folder 471)
      2 p.; 20 x 28 cm.
  - LONGFELLOW, HENRY WADSWORTH, 1807-1882
    - ALS: Cambridge, to Miss Sarah Holland Adams, 1881 Mar 5 (Box 12, Folder 472)
      Thanking Miss Adams for a copy of her
      translations of Grimm's Lectures on
      Goethe, and suggesting that she
      look up an old friend, Mrs. Clara
      Thies at Dresden.
  - LORETZ, JOHANNES, 1727-1798
    - Autograph note, n.d.
      - 2 p.; 9 x 14 cm. Identifying some of the characters in Wilhelm Meister's Lehrjahre with a few contemporaries of Goethe's and Loretz'. The author identifies himself as "Loretz nachheriges Mitglied der Unit[as] Celest[is] Conf[ratum] der Brr.Cem [i.e. Herrnhutischer Apostel, Senior der Bruderunität]."
      - IN: Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von. Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre. Berlin: J.F. Unger, 1795. 1.Bd. Tipped in. (z Nb1 795 1 copy 2)
  - LOWELL, JAMES RUSSELL, 1819-1891
    - ALS: Elmwood, to Bayard Taylor, 1866 Jan 24 (Box 12, Folder 473)
      Discussing Taylor's projected
      translation of Goethe's Faust.
  - LUDECUS, FRAU J. A. (VON KOTZEBUE) VON, 1757-1827
    Full name: Ludecus, Frau Johanna Amalie
    (von Kotzebue) von.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Wilhelm Gottlieb Becker?, 1810 Jul 6 (Box 12, Folder 474)
      Johanna Ludecus, who wrote under the
      pseudonym Amalie von Berg, forwards
      the manuscript of a story.
  - LUDECUS, JOHANN WILHELM CARL, 1768-1854
    - ALS: Weimar, to Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, 1821 Jun 28 (Box 12, Folder 475)
      Official red seal attached.
      Concerns the offer of a coin
      collection from the estate of
      George Batty.
      On p.[3] a ms. note in Kräuter's
      hand, dated Weimar, June 29, 1821,
      signed Goethe, referring the matter
      to Rath Vulpius.
  - LUDEN, HEINRICH, 1778-1847
    - ALS: Jena, to Johann Wilhelm Zinkeisen, 1842 Feb 26 (Box 12, Folder 476)
      1 p.; 13.5 x 21 cm.
      Luden wishes Zinkeisen, the editor of
      Preussische Staatszeitung, to write
      a review of his latest book,
      Geschichte der Teutschen, a copy of
      which he is sending him.
    - Dreissigster, 1815 Nov 30 (Box 12, Folder 477)
      Addressed to Major von Knebel.
      Begins: Hart an das Zimmer gebannt.
      Part of first word in last line is
      mutilated.
    - Autograph certificate concerning Victor Trinks, Jena, 1821 Jun 14 (Box 12, Folder 478)
      1 p.; 13 x 22 cm.
      Attesting that Victor Trinks has
      attended Professor Luden's three
      courses.
  - LUDWIG, OTTO, 1813-1865
    Zwischen Himmel und Erde. n.d.
    - AMs, 2 p.l., 547 p.; 21 x 14 cm. Between heaven and earth. A tale, translated into English from the German of Otto Ludwig. Translator and transcriber unknown.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 821
  - LÜTZELBURG, PH. VON
    - Brasilien und Göthe, [1932] (Box 12, Folder 479)
      244 l. incl. map; 33 cm.
      Annotated bibliography of speeches,
      essays and accounts at the occasion
      of the hundreth anniversary of
      Goethe's death.
  - LYSER, JOHANN PETER THEODOR, 1803-1870